45 but we picked up on מד עמוד ב Mem Daled Amud
Bet a little before the משנה Mishna and at the very bottom.
It's the two dots that say רוח קצרית Ruach Ketzerit or קצרה.
Ketzera. The way it starts is with רוח קצרית. Ruach Ketzerit. It's
about 20 lines from the bottom, three lines over where it has
the 12 in brackets at the beginning of a line. Okay so
it says רוח קצרית באה עליו Ruach Ketzerit ba’ah elav so this
is another מום mum or problem by כהנים Kohanim and again it’s
very interesting here that we’re dealing with very non-visible things, goes into
this more general category of שוה בזרעו של אהרן shave b’zaro shel
Aharon you know that it’s not that it’s something that’s in the
sort of normal range but again it’s interesting what types of things
we’re looking at. So this is a spirit of Ketzerit. Again רש''י
Rashi reads it as some type of demonic spirit but it could
be understood to just mean a shortness of breath like asthma. מני
הוא, Mani hu, what is that? תנא רוח בן נפלים באה אליו
Tanna ruach ben nephalim ba’ah elav the רוח ruach of the בן
נפלים ben nephalim comes to him. So again רש''י Rashi says that
בן נפלים ben nephalim is some type of an evil spirit.
So however you understand that, but again it’s possible to just read
this to mean as I said some type of a shortness of
breath or asthma which would also fit in with the discussion before
about epilepsy. Now what is בן נפלים? ben nephalim? Yeah I don’t
know, meaning I’m not sure that’s what it means in the גמרא
Gemara but at least what it means in the משנה Mishna falling
down. But then the side says נעלה Na’ala but then תנן רוח
נפלים tnan ruach nephalim so נעלה na’ala also either the name of
the spirit is, I’m not saying the גמרא Gemara is not assuming
it’s a spirit I’m just trying to say what exactly is it
that we’re describing?
Like people falling down?
Maybe if that’s how the נפלים nephalim although רש''י Rashi just reads
it as רוח שטות ruach shtus says רש''י, Rashi, או שד זהו
בן נפלים. o sheyd zehu ben nephalim. So רש''י Rashi yeah, so
maybe for רש''י Rashi this is another type of a thrashing of
a you know type of a fit like an epileptic type of
a fit as well.
Okay now המשובנו בעל גבר Hamishuvano ba’al gever getting back to the
urinary and other types of genital areas that we were addressing yesterday
although less directly. So this is משובנו בעל גבר. mushuvano ba’al gever.
So what is this? תנא מושבן או מושובנו בביצים Tanna mushvan o
mushuvano b’beytzim which is large testicles ובעל גבר בגיד uva’al gever b’gid
the penis itself is very large. תנא מושובנו זה הקיין הגרבתן זהו
בלקיק. Tanna mushuvano zeh hakayan hagarbtan zehu balkik. So again other words
given instead of בעל גבר ba’al gever we have the word גרבתן
garbtan which might also be גבר-תן gever-tan or גרבתן garbtan the resh
and the bet tend to transpose. You know גבר gever obviously being
the word for the maleness, the manly the male member organ. So
anyway and so it associates those words with other Hebrew words קיין
kayan and בלקיק. balkik. קיין בביצים Kayan b’beytzim and again it explains,
קיין kayan is with the testicles very large. גרבתא Garbta or you
know again as opposed to גבר, gever, גרבתא בגיד garbta b’gid with
the male or with the penis. ועד כמה, Ve’ad kama, how big
would it have to be for it to be a problem? So
מחוי רבי יהודה עד רכובה machvei Rabbi Yehuda ad rukba until the
knees. Alright now we’re talking pretty big. תניא רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
אומר עד רכובה פסול למעלה מרכובה כשר. Tanya Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
omer ad rukba pasul lemala merukba kasher. No
if it only got up to there if it went if it
went up to there meaning beyond the knees again which part of
the knees then it’s invalid but if it’s above there then it’s
כשר. kasher. איכא דאמרי Ika d’amri some say no,
עד רכובה כשר למטה מן הרכובה פסול. ad rukba kasher lemata min
harukba pasul. More than that it’s invalid. Alright so that we are
talking about a pretty major deformity there or you know difference from
normal from normal men. Moving on, next משנה. Mishna. אין לו ביצים
Ein lo beytzim now we’re still within the testicles if he has
no testicles או אין לו אלא ביצה אחת o ein lo ela
beytza achat and you only one testicle. You might remember that we
had a very similar משנה Mishna by the animals. הרי זה מרוח
אשך Harei zeh meruach ashech
that is the מרוח אשך meruach ashech referred to in the תורה
Torah which is a specific מום. mum. So now by the way
we’re no longer in this category of לא שוה בזרעו של אהרן,
lo shave b’zaro shel Aharon, not similar you know amongst the amongst
you know not sort of the narrow definition of sort of the
narrow range but we’re actually talking about a specific מום. mum. So
what is מרוח אשך? meruach ashech? So it’s understanding that the word
אשך ashech means the testicles and מרוח meruach sometimes like the word
למרוח limroach means to smooth or to press down so it means
crushed, crushed testicles. That’s the first opinion. רבי ישמעאל אומר כל שנמחו
אשכיו Rabbi Yishmael omer kol she’nimchu ashkavav that it’s that his that
his that his testicles have basically
been dissolved. רבי עקיבא אומר כל שרוח באשכיו. Rabbi Akiva omer kol
she’ruach b’ashkavav.
No that they somehow have inflated you know there’s somehow again some
type of a disease or something that has caused them to be
to be swelled or inflated not just that they’re naturally larger. רבי
חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer he has a
totally different explanation of מרוח אשך meruach ashech as it has nothing
to do with the testicles, כל שמראהו חשוכין. kol she’marav chasuchim.
He has a dark appearance. He has a swarthy look and we
were talking in terms of his general. Wait, so this is
dismissed? Well, because he says, not because there's anything to do with
the these problems, but it's a radically different interpretation of this phrase
in the Torah. So we're no longer talking according to him about
let's talk about problems in the genitals, but let's understand this phrase
in the Torah. So this phrase in the Torah מרוח אשך meruach
ashach for him means this totally different thing. And let's see, the
Gemara will point out that it really doesn't belong in this list.
Why is he saying that dark skin is a defect?
Yes, and we're going to talk about that in a minute later
today, we're actually going to talk about about the
Gemara's going to refer to כושי, Cushi, you know, Ethiopians, people of
dark skin. The question is how dark skin, but yes, this gets
into this issue that now we're talking about racial characteristics as well.
You know, so yeah, I agree that this is definitely going to
be a very challenging daf. Let's take a look. קשיא ליה לרבי
ישמעאל. Kashya lei le-Rabbi Yishmael. So Rabbi Yishmael, why did Rabbi Yishmael
reject the first opinion that it meant crushed testicles and he explained
it to mean dissolved testicles? Says חסר אשך מיבעי ליה. Chasar ashach
mibaei lei. If it meant, if it meant, I'm sorry,
no, no, no, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
The first opinion was, I'm sorry, I misread the Mishnah. The first
opinion was, you don't have them at all, it's lacking a testicle.
Then Rabbi Yishmael said כל שנימוחו אשכיו kol she-nimochu ashkav
means that they are dissolved or they're crushed. So the first opinion
actually, right, the side has instead of נימוח, nimoch, which means dissolve,
the Shita Mekubetzet switches it to שנמרחו, she-nimrechu, crushed.
Okay, so the first opinion was missing a testicle, then Rabbi Yishmael
says crushed or dissolved, then Rabbi Akiva says that it actually means
inflated. So let's take a look. So קשיא ליה לרבי ישמעאל. Kashya
lei le-Rabbi Yishmael. So why Rabbi Yishmael rejected the first opinion that
it was missing a testicle? חסר אשך מיבעי ליה. Chasar ashach mibaei
lei. It
should have said lacking, not why did the Torah say מרוח? meruach?
What does מרוח meruach have to do with meaning that it's completely
absent? So therefore תני שנמרחו אשכיו. tani she-nimrechu ashkav. Therefore
you interpret the word מרוח meruach from the word למרוח, limroach, which
means to press down or to crush. Thank you. So which means
crushed testicles. קשיא ליה לרבי עקיבא. Kashya lei le-Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Akiva
didn't like that. היי ממרוח אשך מיבעי ליה. Hai mimruach ashach mibaei
lei.
The mem for למרוח limroach to crush or to press down is
part of the root of the word. So to say to be
pushed down, you would need another mem to serve for the verb,
like if you wanted to say inflated, you would say מנופח. menupach.
Okay, so the you add a mem
to sort of adjectivize it. So if it meant crushed and the
mem was part of the verb, it would have been ממרוח mimruach
or something, ממרוח, mimruach, I don't know. Anyway, so תני, tani, so
therefore he said that it's not from the word למרוח limroach to
crush, but it's from the word רוח, ruach, wind, or like to
be inflated and blown up. So תני שרוח באשכיו, tani she-ruach be-ashkav,
that is his testicles are inflated, are blown.
So קשיא ליה לרבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס. Kashya lei le-Rabbi Chanina ben
Antigonus. Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus didn't like that explanation. היי רוח אשך
מיבעי ליה. Hai ruach ashach mibaei lei. Then what's the mem doing
at all? It should have just said רוח אשך. ruach ashach. I
don't know exactly the grammar here that they're dealing with, but okay.
Anyway, so he didn't like that explanation. So therefore what did he
say it meant? So תני שמראיו חשוכין, tani she-marav hashuchin, that it
means that he has a black, dark appearance. So where does he
get that from the phrase מרוח אשך? meruach ashach?
Is חשוך chashuch like חשוך? chashuch?
So קסבר, kasavar, he's of the opinion גורעין ומוסיפין ודורשין. gorin u-mosifin
ve-dorshin. You can basically rearrange the letters and make your drasha. So
what's that game, Boggle? Or something, anyway, so you can like or
a cross, you know, what are those things where you do rearrange
letters? Anyway, fine. How does, so therefore, how does that work? So
the way Rashi explains is you מרוח אשך, meruach ashach, you reverse
the chet and the aleph. So therefore it would be מראו, maro,
like the appearance, mem-vav-resh-aleph or whatever, or
mem-resh-aleph-vav, מראו, maro, the appearance is חושך, choshech, a dark appearance. So
he gets it by rearranging the letters. So the Gemara says if
that's true, היינו כושי. hainu Cushi. We're going to say in a
later Mishnah the Ethiopian, which is dark-skinned. So Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus
לא תני כושי. lo tani Cushi. He doesn't have that in his
Mishnah. He doesn't need it because he's got this problem, he learns
it out from this pasuk. So really according to him, he has
one less מום, mum, the מום mum relating to the testicles for
him is one less. But here we're talking about an actual מום,
mum, not this problem of שוה בזרעו של אהרן, shaveh be-zaro shel
Aharon, because it's learned out from this case of מרוח אשך meruach
ashach in the Torah. Okay, so right now again, to the degree
that we're just talking about injuries or whatever on the body, you
know, deformities and injuries, that's something that we are used to. But
this new introduction about skin color is obviously very disturbing considering all
the, you know, all we've learned in terms of, you know, racial
issues and equality and slavery and so on. So it feels somehow
much more profoundly offensive than these other things, especially because it relates
to, as we'll see later, you know, when it talks about כושי
Cushi and Ethiopians, entire classes and races of people. It's not just
an individual. We had this yesterday. Well, the nuances was raised by
you guys, it was not in the Mishnah. Okay, I understand. So
let's, so let's see about that.
So
that we will, I'm sure we will have some vigorous discussion.
No those were just naturally very large.
And these are these
are like some type of infection that causes them to be you
know inflated or something.
Oh so it might be a מום עובר mum over then potentially.
Could be but you're פסול pasul with a מום עובר. mum over.
Okay מקיש בקרסוליו makish bekarsulav now we're moving I guess down the
body although we haven't really like been we've somewhat been consistent we've
been the head, the eyes, the nose, you know we've slow somewhat
been moving down the body. So now we go below the waist
and continuing there we're talking about the legs. So if somebody's basically
knees knock, you know knees knocking, מקיש בקרסוליו, makish bekarsulav, ובערקובותיו u've'arkovotav
or ankles knock when you walk you sort of are banging your
ankles to one another, ובעל הפיקוס u'vaal hapikas and the person who
is the פיקוס pikas top of מ"א ע"א, mem amud aleph, והעיקל
veha'ikal and the עיקל, ikal, so what are those? So again רש"י
Rashi says oh the משנה Mishna will explain. It's great another רש"י
Rashi like the next line in the משנה Mishna but he assumes
you're I guess reading him like word for word so he tells
you the משנה's Mishna's going to explain and look here it does.
איזהו העיקל eizehu ha'ikal what is the עיקל? ikal? כל שמקיש פרסותיו
ואין ארכובותיו נוקשות זו לזו. kol shemakish parsotav ve'ein arkovotav nokshot zo
lezo. So it's not that your knees knock or that your ankles
knock but that when you sit together and you put your ankles
together your knees point outwards. You're bowlegged.
Okay, very similar to those other things again presumably here not a
מום mum but the problem about שוה בשאר
אחיו shaveh bish'ar echav like none of these were mentioned by the
animals. And פיקא pika now what is this case of פיקוס? pikas?
So that seems to be very different. I mean פיקא יוצא מגוודלו.
pika yotzei migudlo. He has some type of a spherical growth coming
out of his thumb. So that's like really completely unrelated to all
the rest because we talked about hands before and arms and so
on. So I don't know exactly where that's you know why that
is in this list.
Maybe it's a thing that comes out of your toe? Presumably yeah.
So I don't know.
I guess it's an interesting thing to keep it on the feet
maybe it does mean big toe which
but yeah it's not clarified here. I was assuming it meant and
the גמרא's Gemara's going to quote a ברייתא braita about שבר יד
או שבר רגל shever yad o shever regel which relates to hands
as well. So I assume it means here the thumb. But again
why דווקא davka the thumb? How about any finger? How about the
feet? I don't know. So okay now moving but anyway continuing your
focus on the feet what I don't know does Artscroll say that
means the big toe? What do they say there?
They're saying toe to
keep it in the context of feet. Okay fine I can accept
that. All right anyway
yeah.
So interesting how like it mentions the second word first and the
first word.
Yeah did that before in the last משנה Mishna also.
Yeah I don't know.
Okay now
עקבו יוצא לאחוריו akevo yotzei leachorav let's say his heel comes from
comes out
protrudes outwards which basically means that your leg is attached to your
foot but if you think about it right our leg is attached
to the foot the back of the bone of the leg bone
is attached to the back of the foot. So this imagines a
case where the where the where the leg bone was center in
the foot so that the rear the ankle would protrude outwards you
know sort of like if you're making a toy out of Tinker
Toys or whatever you know and you put the you sort of
like a base to a to a column where you got the
leg bone going straight in and the front of the foot and
the back of the foot come out equally from the leg bone.
Okay.
Were many deformities back then that they mentioned all these?
No I don't think so. I mean that's an interesting question Mr.
Charlie here maybe he could speak about like about different health care
conditions and so on did it lead to greater birth defects? Yeah
yeah I don't know it's an interesting question but I think that
they're just like they always do in הלכה halacha you know sort
of fleshing out excuse the pun or whatever you know spelling out
all of the range of possibilities.
That you wouldn't even see nowadays.
Exactly. It's a good point too like what what are you even
imagining might be the case if you've never seen any of these?
What you know right you would have to perhaps see some of
this type of stuff in order to imagine it. But clearly there
I mean the control of you know different types of things infections
and diseases or whatever I mean you know we know that that
was horrific but but whether that led to like birth deformities or
whatever that I don't know. That's a very interesting question. Yes.
Spherical growth is that like a tumor or something?
Sounds like like an external maybe but I'm not sure it'd have
to be cancerous or whatever but yes something like that. Yeah exactly.
Exactly. Okay now פרסותיו רחבות כשל אווז parsotav rechavot keshel avaz
let's say the person's feet are are wide like a duck. Yes
duck feet basically and the גמרא Gemara will say should say what
that means. Is it toe? Yeah I mean you ever seen like
webbed either webbed the גמרא Gemara webbed is it? Right so the
גמרא Gemara will talk about two conditions. One is that it's very
flat and and wide you know what a duck's sort of thing
looks like flat and wide not arched not narrow and so on
you know and the other is the webbed aspect. So the גמרא
Gemara will sort of discuss both. אצבעותיו מורכבות זו על גבי זו
etzbe'otav murkavot zo al gabi zo
let's say the fingers are sort of like this they you know
I don't know I is that a condition where somebody's fingers grow
like one on top of the other you know and they don't
normally lie side by side.
So Rashi says it means from the palm to the knuckle, meaning
what's above what's below? What's above the top or the bottom? I
mean I just called this the top. But anyway Rashi says למעלה
lemala means like I guess if you're holding your hand down it
means from the palm from the hand to the first joint they're
fused. Okay. Now here it's very hard to understand how to read
this and the גמרא Gemara doesn't help too much. כשר. Kasher. Now
what's כשר? kasher? Is it כשר kasher going on the first phrase,
on what's coming next? It sounds like at minimally it's going on
what came before, at least the last phrase of what came before,
that if it's fused from the palm to the to the knuckle
that is okay. Why? Why is not clear. Okay because maybe it
doesn't again at least your fingers how you use them. I mean
although it's true you need sometimes to get range on your fingers
but at least to some degree although you imagine if it's conjoined
at the knuckle you can't get too much range of use.
Right, so I think it means conjoined like you probably have the
skin.
Well yeah there's something there is something that combines it right because
we'll talk in a minute about cutting it. למטה מן הפרק, Lemata
min haperek, if it's from the knuckle to the to the fingertips,
וחתכה כשר, ve-chatachah kasher, and then you severed that joint, that then
it's כשר. kasher. Which suggests that what? That the below even if
it remains joined is also כשר. kasher. So that's interesting. Again the
types of things that are a problem. An outie belly button is
a problem. Fused fingers until the knuckle, that's okay.
Anyway yeah that wouldn't be okay for נשיאת כפים? nesi'at kapayim? Yeah
it wouldn't if we're really worried about like between the hand, if
anything that should definitely be there.
Right, that could be, but we said the other day that the
נשיאת כפים nesi'at kapayim issues are different, they have much more to
do with distraction. Yeah could be. Yes.
Is it also true
for the whole thing for the feet?
Oh by the feet and the toes. Again I guess the same
issue. That's a good point. Same like they tried to do by
the גודל? godel? That does keep it in the same range. Does
that help explain why it's not such a problem? I guess since
you don't really use, you know, your toes are less visible and
you don't really need the same type of range. You don't you
don't you don't sort of spread your toes or whatever, you just
need the basic maybe grasping which is done with the tips of
them. So maybe that explains it. Right. That's a nice explanation. Oh
you mean and that connects to the to the webbed feet of
the duck's feet. Oh that's nice. That's a nice explanation. I accept
that. That's nice. Okay and it also helps explain why the fused
near the, you know, near the base is more כשר kasher because
you don't need the range, you know, that type of movement of
your toes as you do...
wouldn't necessarily mean if it was on your hands it would be
okay though.
Right, correct.
Yeah. Okay so that's a very that's a good explanation. I accept
that. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. היתה בו יתרת וחתכה, Haitah bo yeteret ve-chatachah, if there was
an extra digit, and here we're going to see clearly includes also
the hand, so if you cut it off then אם יש בה
עצם פסול ואם לאו כשר. im yesh bah etzem pasul ve-im lav
kasher. If there was a bone in it and you cut it
off it's פסול. pasul. Why? Because now you're lacking a bone, now
you're lacking a limb. The fact that it had an extra digit
with a bone defined it as a limb and now you're actually
lacking a limb and that's a מום, mum, even though now you
look more you know normal, quote unquote, but the fact that you've
cut off a limb. If you didn't, then it's just halachically defined
as an extra hanging piece of flesh and therefore if you cut
it off it's not lacking a limb and you're כשר. kasher. Now
let's say you didn't cut it off. Right. Would that be a
problem? So that implicitly is a problem and that we and you
will sort of see from the from the next line
more of that. So let's see the next line. יתירה בידו וברגליו
שש שש עשרים וארבע. Yeterah beyado uv-raglav shesh shesh esrim ve-arba. If
you have an extra digit in your hands and feet, six on
each hand and on each foot, so that you have twenty four
digits, so that רבי יהודה מכשיר וחכמים פוסלין. Rabbi Yehuda machshir va-chachamim
poslin. Rabbi Yehuda says it's כשר kasher and Sages say it's not
good. Now presumably it doesn't mean even up to six on each
hand, presumably it only means this case because if you had just
one hand that had an extra or maybe even an extra on
each hand but not on the feet or vice versa, it would
go to the discussion before about the lack of pairing and of
parallel and of symmetry. Right, remember that before we had this need
of symmetry. So that would presumably be a problem although one does
wonder let's say you had it just on the hands and not
on the feet or vice versa, but maybe we look at all
the digits and they have to sort of be you know symmetrical
in all directions. But if it's an extra on every single hand
and foot, so then maybe okay, maybe that's not maybe that's not
a פסול, pasul, everything is symmetrical, okay? Which is again quite funny
you know that a normal variation like an outie belly button, I
got to keep on going back to that, that's a problem. You
know, that's enough of a variation. But this because it's all symmetrical,
anyway that's just Rabbi Yehuda's position, the Sages say it's invalid. And
now we get to השולט בשתי ידיו רבי פוסל וחכמים מכשירין. Ha-sholet
bi-shtei yadav Rebbi posel va-chachamim machshirin. Ambidextrous, Rebbi says it's not good,
the Sages say it's good, with the implicit point being which will
be spelled out in the משנה Mishnah that a left-handed person is
definitely not good and we will talk about that. So now we
are getting to a very interesting range of issues you know in
the foot and the hand and by the way I will say
that clearly at the... again when we're talking about ambidextrous, we're also
talking about, we're talking about only hands, although the גמרא Gemara actually,
because שתי ידיו, Shtei Yadav, although the גמרא Gemara will talk about
questions about, is a person favor his left when he walks as
well as when he right, you know, in terms of his leg
and not just his arm. But anyway, but but I do ex-
I do think that it's a better read as James was saying
that the earlier issues were speaking specifically about the toes. All right,
so there's a lot to talk about. Let's take it case by
case and see what the גמרא Gemara says. תנו רבנן, Tano Rabbanan,
שבר רגל. Shever Regel. It says או שבר רגל או שבר יד,
O Shever Regel O Shever Yad, right? Broken arm or leg. So
we're going to now use that to be a basis for interpreting
the whole range of things by the arms and legs and feet
and hands. אין לי אלא שבר רגל. Ein li ela Shever Regel.
מנין לרבות הקישן והעיקל? Minayin l'rabot ha-kishan v'ha-ikal? How do I know
to include the קישן kishan which is the knock-knees or the knocking
ankles or the עיקל, ikal, which is the person again which is
bow-legged, right? הקילבן, Ha-kilban, and קילבן kilban we haven't talked about yet,
we'll talk about that in a minute. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, although
actually no, the גמרא Gemara doesn't explain קילבן. kilban. I saw somebody
that tried to translate קילבן kilban as
club-footed. What is club-footed exactly? I should know, my twin brother was
born with club feet but I don't- he had many operations. Are
the feet straight? They point outwards. Oh, that would sort of be
like the- the pigeon-foot, yeah.
No, that's
the toe-
pigeon-foot is pointed in, you know. Oh,
maybe.
That would be the parallel of bow-legged though, which is just the
natural outward pointing of the feet rather than whatever. Anyway, תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, או שבר רגל. O Shever Regel. The או O includes
other problems with the feet. תניא, Tanya, so it's taught, בעל הפיקין
Baal Ha-Pikin something, which is again the growth of the משנה, Mishnah,
that big spherical growth, והשופנר, v'ha-shufnar, and the שופנר. shufnar. What is
the שופנר? shufnar?
So the גמרא's Gemara going to say, אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba Amar Yochanan, בעל הפיקין שיש
לו כסותות הרבה. Baal Ha-Pikin she-yesh lo k'sotot harbeh. So actually it
says פיקן, pikan, our משנה Mishnah said פיכס, pikas, which- which was-
so the גמרא Gemara here says פיקן pikan presumably is something different,
שיש לו כסותות הרבה. she-yesh lo k'sotot harbeh. He has a big
calf. שופנר שאין לו כסותות כל עיקר. Shufnar she-ein lo k'sotot kol
ikar. Calf, K-A-L-F, right? Meaning the- the sort of the fleshy part
here, what? We say C-A-L-F. C, right. The fleshy part here on
your lower leg. So is it extremely large or is it basically
you have- or the other one is easier to understand why it's
a problem, that he's basically like a- like a- like what they
say, like a- like a chicken leg essentially, you know, there's really
like no muscle in the calf. Elephantiasis? Oh, is that- is that
what it looks like? Yeah. Oh.
Not just that you work out a lot and you have a
big
muscle.
Right, no. אוי, Oy, anyway, so
פיקה יוצא מגודלו ועקב יוצא לאחוריו. pika yotzei mi-godlo v'akev yotzei l'achorav.
So here we have the growth or your heel coming out from
your back. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, שוקו יוצא באמצע רגלו.
shoko yotzei b'emtza raglo. So there his שוק, shok, which here by
the way, which means clearly your lower leg, that's important, the whole
גמרא Gemara in ברכות Brachot about שוק באשה ערוה shok b'isha ervah
and so on, I just actually wrote something about that, I'll send
it to you. Anyway, so the שוק shok really means the lower
leg, not the thigh as it's often translated. So the lower leg
goes into the middle of the foot, right? As opposed to the
back of the- of the lower leg with the back of the
heel, no, it's like smack in the middle of the foot. Okay,
now we get פרסתו רחבות
כשל אווז. parsetav r'chavot k'shel avaz. You have web-footed or duck- you
know, duck-like feet. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, לא תימא
דטריפא ולא סדיקא. lo teima d'treifa v'lo sidika. Don't say that it
means that they are sort of that it is flat and
wide, somewhat what the word טריפא treifa means, and not- and also
not סדיקא, sidika, meaning web-footed. אלא כיון דטריפא אף על גב דסדיקא.
Ela keivan d'treifa af al gav d'sidika. Even if the toes are
separated, you're not web-footed, but if it's flat and wide as opposed
to being sort of like, you know, thick and narrow, which is
our feet look like, that is itself a problem. Presumably web-footed as
well is a problem, and reading אצבע etzba here as, you know,
as the toes, that's actually the next line in the משנה. Mishnah.
אצבעותיו מורכבות זו על גב זו. Etzba'otav murkavot zu al gav zu.
The fingers or the toes, let's say the digits, are fused one
on top of the other, or not even fused but just somehow
the bone structure has them riding one on top of the other.
או קלוטות, O klutot, or if they are fused. תנו רבנן, Tano
Rabbanan, שבר יד. Shever Yad. A broken hand. אין לי אלא שבר
יד. Ein li ela Shever Yad. אצבעותיו מורכבות. Etzba'otav murkavot. So we
see here now we're talking about- now we're doing it on יד.
yad. So that whole question about whether this whole משנה Mishnah is
talking about just toes or also fingers, that's why I said the
גמרא Gemara sort of brings in the hand as well. אצבעותיו מורכבות
או קלוטות Etzba'otav murkavot o klutot למעלה מן הפרק. l'maala min ha-perek.
או קלוטות, O klutot, if they are either, you know, riding one
on top of the other or they are
webbed. למעלה מן הפרק. L'maala min ha-perek. רש"י Rashi says here למעלה
l'maala means what the משנה Mishnah meant by למטה, l'mata, which means
actually, which actually means from the- from the digit, from the knuckle
down to the- to the nails. וחתכן. V'chatchan. And you cut them,
that's a problem. So גמרא Gemara says one minute, you cut them.
והאמרת כשר veha’amarta kasher דהא משנתינו, deha mishnateinu, our משנה Mishna says
that if you cut it, it's כשר. kasher. אלא בלא
חתכן, ela belo chatchan, if you didn't cut it, מנא לן, menalan,
how do you know it's a problem? תלמוד לומר או שבר ידו,
talmud lomar o sheber yado, if it's riding on top of one
another or they are fused at the top and uncut, then it
is a problem. But if you cut it, it's okay. Presumably fused
from the knuckle towards the actual foot or palm, that would be
okay. Again, it sounds like we're talking about
including, not excluding, that's from the knuckle to the finger, to the
nails, to the tip. There you have to cut it, but from
the, from the knuckles back to the actual palm or foot, that
at least, again, the word כשר kasher in the משנה, Mishna, it's
hard to read what is the word כשר kasher going on in
the משנה. Mishna. It actually would be a much better if, I
don't know, I didn't check the different משניות, mishnayot, but this would
read a lot better if the word כשר kasher was not there.
Then it would just be וכל תות למעלה עד הפרק vechol tut
lemalah ad haperek period, למטה מן הפרק וחתכן כשר. lematah min haperek
vachatchan kasher. The משנה Mishna would read a lot better if that
word כשר kasher wasn't there. But with that word כשר, kasher, it
sounds like it's saying that from the knuckle to the hand or
from the knuckle to the foot, it actually is okay. And again,
the גמרא Gemara seems to be talking about including the fingers of
the hand, but if it's talking about the toes, it's understandable because
as we said, like you don't really need much, it's not visible
and you don't really need much range with your toes. Okay, so
now we go on.
Where are we? היתה
בו יתרת וחתכה, hayta bo yeteret vachatchan, if there was an extra
limb. Now we're getting into the really interesting discussions about the extra
limbs. If there was an extra digit and you cut it off,
אם יש בה עצם פסול, im yesh bah etzem pasul, if there's
a bone, it's a problem because then you're, you're missing a limb.
It is considered a limb. Again, the implicit point is that if
you didn't cut it off, it's also פסול pasul until you get
to the case of everything of six, six, six, and six. But
normally, presumably if you didn't cut it off, it's a פסול. pasul.
ואם לאו, ve’im lav, and if it did not have a limb
and you cut it off, then כשר, kasher, it's כשר. kasher. Okay,
now what if, what if it didn't have, what if it didn't
have a bone? If it didn't have a bone and you cut
it off, then it's okay. What if it didn't have a bone
and you didn't cut it off? So that would be like a
hanging piece of, of, you know, flesh.
Is that a problem? So that's going to be a later משנה
Mishna that we discussed before, that presumably that is also a problem
just like an unusual big hanging piece of flesh is also a
problem. So the implicit point is that you have to cut this
off or else to even have the discussion whether it's כשר, kasher,
and then it will matter if it, if it had a bone
then you're missing a limb, no, if it didn't then you're okay.
But if you didn't cut it off, the implicit point is that
it is not כשר. kasher.
Unless there's extra flesh anywhere it's bad. Right, in your stomach, your
chest, yesterday we read that.
Right, exactly, exactly. What about the hunchback again? We said that was
okay, didn't we? Without, there was a debate if it didn't have
a, right, if it with, without, you're right. And the גמרא Gemara
said that דלדול בשר בעלמא הוא. dildul basar be’alma hu. That's a
good point. And there the גמרא Gemara just said that the, although
that was in debate, but that apparently was it was just hanging
flesh. So there's a good point, how much is hanging flesh in
general an issue? The on the next משנה Mishna does say that
you know, where is it? Where's the next משנה? Mishna? Yeah, בעלי
הדלדולין פסולין באדם. ba’ale hadildulim pesulim ba’adam. And the דלדולין dildulim means
חילטולין, hiltulim, רש״י Rashi says, כמו חתיכת בשר יוצאת ותלויה להם, kmo
chatichat basar yotze vetalot lahem, hanging pieces of flesh, those are a
problem. So no, it says it's פסול. pasul. So again, so your
good point that the גמרא Gemara by the the hunchback, there was
an opinion that that wasn't a problem. Right. So that's always a
question, like at what stage is this within a normal acceptable range
versus is this considered trivial and at what stage is it considered
significant? And I guess most people are not hunchbacks.
I know,
I know, I, but again, it was debated there, but I and
I think the סתם stam position was that it was no good.
That it's only רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that said it was
good. Yeah, בעל חותרת, ba’al choteret, it was the first משנה. Mishna.
Yeah, the חכמים chachamim said it's no good. So at least we
have a consistent position that these unusual growths of skin are no
good. So the assumption here is that it's no good if you
don't cut and if you do cut it matters if it has
a bone or not. So let's take a look at what the
גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, והוא שנספרו על גבי היד.
vehu shenisperu al gabei hayad. The only way it would be considered
a limb that if you cut it off you'd be considered lacking
a limb would be if it was counted with the fingers of
the hand, meaning you like held up your hand and they would
be in a row with the other fingers. But if it would
be coming out of some unusual place and it would not be
in a normal row with the fingers, we would never have considered
it a limb to begin with and therefore if you cut it
out off you'd be okay.
Even if it had a bone. What? Even if it had a
bone. Yeah, even if it had a bone. If it didn't have
a bone then wherever it is it's not a limb, but you
still might have to cut it off. But if it had a
bone, it's only considered a limb if it's together with the fingers
of the hand, okay, counted together with them. Okay, תנו רבנן, tana
rabbanan, יתרת שיש בה עצם ואין בה צפורן, yeteret sheyesh ba etzem
ve’ein bah tziporen, an extra limb, digit that has a bone and
even if it does not have a fingernail, is still considered a
limb and therefore מטמא, metame, now we're talking about a case where
it came off of a dead corpse, מטמא במגע ובמשא, metame bemaga
ubemasa, touching and carrying, ומטמא באוהל, umetame be’ohel, everything under the same,
the same roof, ועולה למנין רמ״ח, ve’ola liminyan ramach, and counts towards.
ועולה למניין קכ״ה ve'oleh le'minyan kuf-chaf-hei and it counts towards 125. What
does this mean? It means that parts of a dead body cause
טומאה tumah if you touch them. How much? A כזית kezayis of
the flesh, the tiniest, an עצם etzem gives off or a tiny
piece of bone the size of a barley seed, but, but, there
you have to get to a certain size or certain significance so
that it's considered representative of the entire body, so that under a
roof everything becomes טמא, tamei, not just through touch, but everything under
the roof, טומאת אהל. tumas ohel.
How much is that? Well, if it is any limb, even a
very small limb, and even if it does not have a flesh
enough of a כזית, kezayis, that is still considered an אבר מן
המת, eiver min ha'meis,
excuse me, a limb, not an עצם etzem that's a bone, a
limb of a dead body causes טומאת אהל tumas ohel even without
touching. So here it says if the person had this dead person
actually had a sixth digit and it was cut off, that would
cause טומאה tumah under, that is still considered a limb, like we
said here, if you cut it off you'd be considered lacking the
limb, if it was cut off it'd be a limb and would
cause טומאה tumah under under an אהל, ohel, even if there's not
a כזית kezayis of flesh in order to do that by itself
by virtue of the flesh. Okay? So that is what it means
that it is I'm going to say that's what it means טומאת
אהל. tumas ohel. What does this mean 125? Another way you can
cause טומאת אהל tumas ohel is if you have the majority of
the limbs of the bones of the body. Now how many bones
are there according to the rabbis in the body? We say it
when we say מי שברך, Mi Sheberach, רמ״ח איברים ושס״ה גידים, ramach
eivarim ve'shasa gidav, 248 איברים, eivarim, limbs, okay, so
248 bones that generally mean. Now, 248 divided by 2 is anybody?
124. So the majority of the bones, רוב עצמות, rov atzamot, even
if they're stripped of flesh, the majority of the bones also causes
טומאת אהל. tumas ohel. So if you had if the person had
this extra limb and you added this bone from this extra limb,
that's considered part of the body and would make it 125. Interestingly,
even if because of this extra limb they actually have now more
than 248 bones, right, so you might need a higher number to
get to the majority of bones, you go as we'll see later
by the standard number. So the standard number of bones that causes
טומאה tumah in an אהל ohel is 124,
125, 124 is half, 125. And therefore when a person has this
extra limb, it does not change the number 125 and not only
does it not change the number, but this bone can count towards
that number. Okay, so that is how this is applied in the
laws of טומאת אהל. tumas ohel. From
one body or from two bodies? No, no, no, from משני מתים,
mishnei meisim, that's the debate in the משנה. Mishnah. We have to
assume from one body. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Even if you cut it off? Just starting from, you know, it
has to be buried in general, right? Yeah.
Well,
if you cut off on a live אבר מן החי, eiver min
hachai, if you're calling considering it to be a limb, yes. If
you're considering it to be a limb.
Okay, that would be another interesting
question, whether it would have the status of אבר מן החי. eiver
min hachai. Anyway, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
So, אמר רבא בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chanah amar Rabbi Yochanan, ובנספרת על גב היד, u've'nisperes al gav
hayad, that's again, only if it's counted with the fingers of the
hand does it have this status of a limb for those two
הלכות halachos of טומאת אהל tumas ohel that we just mentioned. אמר
רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, דבר זה רבנו הגדול אמרו, Davar zeh
Rabbeinu HaGadol amro, this following thing I'm about to say our great
rabbi said, המקום יהיה בעזרו, HaMakom yiheyeh be'ezro, God should be at
his side, which is a nice little like thing. Now who is
the רבנו הגדול? Rabbeinu HaGadol? So רש״י Rashi says it's רב, Rav,
but רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says it's רבי. Rebbi. So I would,
you know, it's funny, I would assume that if it's רב חסדא
Rav Chisda saying it, the רבנו הגדול Rabbeinu HaGadol would be רבי,
Rebbi, not רב, Rav, which is more a bit contemporary than of
a than of a teacher. But anyway, whoever it is, either רב
Rav or רבי, Rebbi, they were, you know, רב Rav was the
next generation. Anyway, he said the following thing. יסרת שיש בה עצם
ואין בה ציפורן, Yisres she'yesh bah etzem ve'ein bah tziporen, again, you
have this extra digit that has a bone and does not have
a nail, מטמא במגע ובמשא ואינה מטמא באהל, metamei be'maga u've'massa ve'einah
metamei be'ohel, it causes טומאה tumah if you touch and carrying, but
not under a tent, which is different than what we just said
before. אמר רבא בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chanah amar Rabbi Yochanan, so we're going to reconcile it, בשאינה
נספרת על גב היד. be'she'einah nisperes al gav hayad. It's the same
thing, it's a digit with with with a bone, but it's not
with the fingers of the hand, it's not in a row with
the fingers of the hand, so it never really counts as a
limb and therefore does not cause טומאה tumah in the tent. אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so said רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, which
is quite interesting that this is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying it
because he's referring to a statement that was just made a minute
ago in his own name. So the צד tzad which is the
גרסא girsa תאמר רבי חנינא ta'amar Rabbi Chanina and not אמר רבי
יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan because he anyway, here's what רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina said, עשו דבריהם כדברי נביאות. Asu divreihem ke'divrei nevi'os. What they
just said, that's like words of prophecy. As תוספות Tosafos says, that
was not meant as a compliment. Which means it's like, you know,
you're just saying it like not based on anything. It's like a
prophet comes and says, this is the way things are. You know,
so what do you what's the reason for any of this? Which
is why it sounds like it's not רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan because
he's commenting on a statement that was said in his own name.
Now, ממה נפשך, mamah nafshach, make up your mind about this limb
that is not counted with the fingers of the hand. אי אבר
הוא, ei eiver hu, if you consider it a genuine limb, so
באהל נמי. be'ohel nami. let it cause טומאה tum'ah under the roof.
ואי לאו איבר הוא, ve-ee lav eivar hu, if because it's not
counted with the fingers of the hand it's not a limb, so
במגע ומשא נמי לא תיטמא, b'maga u-massa nami lo titama, why does
it cause טומאה tum'ah through touch and through carrying, right, it shouldn't
cause טומאה tum'ah if it's not a limb. So it's a funny
question because the answer seems to be pretty straightforward. So let's see
what the answer is. Right, you understand if it's not a limb,
why does it cause any טומאה? tum'ah? So here's the answer of
the גמרא. Gemara. So, אמר רב הונא בר מנוח משמיה דרב אחא
בריה דרב איקא, amar Rav Huna bar Manoach mishmei de-Rav Acha brei
de-Rav Ika, משום עצם כשעורה נגו בה. mishum etzem kes'orah nago bah.
So נגו בה nago bah is a funny phrase because we're talking
about טומאת מגע tumas maga touch, but נגו בה nago bah means
sort of that's how they that's sort of how they approach it.
They approached it but not because it's a limb, it doesn't have
a status of a limb, but it still has a bone in
it, and it's a bone of the body, and a bone of
the body even if it's very small, even if it's the size
of like a barley bean, causes טומאה tum'ah through touch and through
carrying. So you're right, the reason it causes טומאה tum'ah through touch
and carrying is not because it's a quasi-limb. It's not a limb
at all, but it's still a bone of the body. We're not
going to say it's like not part of the body, right? There's
you know, how do you look at this extra thing? Do you
look at it as like oh, that was an aberration we're not
even considering it part of the body at all? No. If that
were true, maybe you're right, maybe it wouldn't cause even טומאה tum'ah
by touch, but we're not going that far, we're just saying it's
not a limb because it's not counted with the hand. But it's
still part of the body, so it's a bone. So a bone
that does not cause טומאה tum'ah under a tent, but it causes
טומאה tum'ah through carrying and through touching. So that's why it has
that middle state when it's not counted with the body. That's what
he says. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, now רב פפא Rav
Pappa says, גזירה שאינה נספרת אטו נספרת. gezeira she-einah nisperes atu nisperes.
No, it's not based on the bone, it is based on the
limb, but it's rabbinic that we're going to make say that even
though it's not counted with fingers of the hand, it has some
טומאה tum'ah rabbinically because if we gave it no טומאה, tum'ah, you'd
be lenient even with a case, however often this happens I don't
know, but you'd be lenient even with a case when it was
counted with the fingers of the hand. So we have to give
it some טומאה tum'ah rabbinically because it can be confused with the
other case. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, ee hachi, if
that's true, שאינה נספרת באוהל נמי ליטמא? she-einah nisperes bo-ohel nami litamei?
So if that's true, even if it's not counted with the fingers
of the hand, let it have טומאה tum'ah even under a tent
if we're making a safeguard, you know, so it shouldn't be confused
with the case where it is counted with the hand. So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא דרבנן היכירא עבידו ליה כי היכי דלא לשרוף
עליה תרומה וקדשים. lo d'rabbanan hekeira avid'u lei ki heichi d'lo lisrof
alei terumah ve-kodshim. Like we saw a week or two ago, that
sometimes for rabbinic טומאה, tum'ah, they don't make it exactly the same
as biblical, so you understand that it's only rabbinic so you don't
come to burn תרומה terumah if it touched and you were טמא
tamei only as a virtue of this, you should understand that it's
only rabbinic טומאה. tum'ah. So now we are saying that according to
him, it sounds like why doesn't he say the simple point before?
Okay, it's not a limb but you still have a bone of
the dead body. It sounds like he's saying that if this is
not counted with the fingers of the hand, not only is it
not a limb, but it's not even really considered part of the
body at all, which is a fascinating position. And the only reason
it would be טמא tamei would be because of a גזירה, gezeira,
it'll lead to the case of of of a finger, a digit
which is in line with the other fingers of the hand. So
it's that's what it sounds like. It sounds like he is really
saying that you don't have this middle case where it's part of
the body but not a limb. If it was not a, you
know, if it was, I mean, let's let me give you another
scenario. Let's say a person actually had like a like a growth
that was hanging from him, you know, that was sort of you
know, off of his arm, and the person died, and then you
cut that growth off. Would that have the status of a כזית
kezayis of of flesh that would cause טומאה tum'ah in the tent?
Or would you say no, that's not really his flesh, that's just
some growth? Okay, so that seems to be the position being taken
here. If it's not counted with the fingers of the hand, not
only is it not a limb, but maybe it's not really part
of the body at all, maybe even the bone is not an
issue, and the only טומאה tum'ah that we're doing that it would
have would be a rabbinic טומאה tum'ah because it would lead to
cases of counted with the hand. Yes? Why wouldn't you see it
as part of the body? I don't know, that's what I'm asking
because it's not natural because it's seen as a growth, although having
some type of a growth is different which comes later in life
and comes whatever as opposed to something that you're actually born with.
Right? So I really don't understand why the second position rejected the
argument of the טומאה tum'ah of the bone, unless you were saying
no, if it was just about the bone, then if you didn't
touch the bone, just touched the flesh around the bone, you wouldn't
be טמא. tamei. And maybe he says yes, if you touch the
bone directly I would agree, but why does it say you're טמא
tamei even if you just touch the flesh without touching the bone?
So maybe there's also a rabbinic טומאה. tum'ah. So it's not clear
to me whether this second opinion is rejecting the idea that the
bone causes טומאה tum'ah or he's just adding to it. In addition
to the bone, the limb itself is a problem even without touching
the bone rabbinically. Okay so now we go on. תנן התם, tenan
hasam, we taught over there, again in אהלות. Ohalos. רוב בניינו ורוב
מניינו של מת, rov binyano ve-rov minyano shel mes, most of the
of the of the stature of the of the skelet of the
skeleton of the dead body, we're talking about just bones, או o
the vav here means or, or the majority of the number of
bones, causes טומאה tum'ah in טומאת אוהל, tumas ohel, טומאה tum'ah under
a roof, אף על פי שאין בו רובע, af al pi she-ein
bo rova, even if there's not a רובע rova which is a
certain volume So whether it's a certain volume of the bones or
the number of bones, the majority of the number, or bones that
make up the majority of the height. So טמאי, tamei, that causes
טומאה tumah in an אהל. ohel. What is this? תנו רבנן, Tano
rabanan, איזו רוב בניינו? eizu rov binyano? What's most of the structure?
שתי שוקיים וירך אחד, Shti shokayim veyarech echad, שתי ירך אחד, shtei
yarech echad, two lower legs and one ירך, yarech, one thigh. Now
I don't get that because even if most of a person's height
is in their legs, and people are different that way, right? Do
you know? Are most people's height in their legs or in their
upper torso? Or does it depend on person to person? Nobody knows.
Anyway, the גמרא Gemara is assuming that the majority of your height
is in your legs. So if you have the skeletal structure up
to the sort of, you know, of the legs, that's most of
the height, רוב בניינו. rov binyano. But still, I don't get, well
why not שש? sheish? Why not why not שתי יריכיים? shtei yereichim?
Why do you need both thighs? It sounds like we're talking about
within the legs, which themselves are the majority of the height, you
need the majority of them. So I, but I don't get it.
You would think you would need both thighs and both lower legs.
Or just one שוק shok and one ירך. yarech. Maybe that's the
most of the height. Well, I guess because you could hop around
on one leg, right? So I don't get exactly why it's that.
So but anyway, that's for רוב, rov, that's for רוב בניינו. rov
binyano. One minute, so let's take a look. הואיל ורוב גובהו בגודל,
Ho'il verov govho begodel, רש"י Rashi says, not בגדול. begadol. Since that's
most of the height, you know, in a person when they are
sort of, you know, in their height, בגודל, begodel, you know, in
sort of measuring it lengthwise as opposed to other ways of measuring
the structure. איזו רוב מניינו? Eizu rov minyano? What is the majority
of the number? קכ"ה, Kuf chaf hei, 125, because we're assuming 248
bones in the body. It's interesting when you, people talk about, there's
discussions in rabbinic literature about sort of representation and votes and voting
within Jewish communities and who has the, who has like more of
a say in policy matters. They talk about רוב בניין rov binyan
and רוב מניין. rov minyan. So רוב מניין rov minyan is the,
you know, sort of democracy, it's just one man, one vote, goes
by the number, and רוב בניין rov binyan are the people that
have influence and money and so on and are the most of
the structure. So who gets more of a say in governance? It's
an interest, they use those as metaphors. Yeah, I wonder if it
also work, let's say you have just one, you know, just one
side of the leg and then maybe like an arm, you know?
Right, and what if you do have that? Right, so yeah, what
if it's not the exact stuff that the way you put it
together combines, yeah. So I don't know. I'm still trying to figure
out why it's only three out of those four leg bones. Anyway,
let's take a look. We're going to focus on the 125. אמר
ליה רבינא לרבא. Amar lei Ravina le-Rava. So רבינא Ravina said to
רבא, Rava, תנא מניינא אתא לאשמועינן? tano minyana atei le-ashmi'inan? Why does
he bother mentioning 125? We know how to count. So once we
know a general principle of 248 bones, who has to tell us
125? So אמר ליה, amar lei, maybe. So anyway, presumably he took
that for as a given. So the גמרא Gemara says, so it
says, no, הא קמשמע לן כדתניא, ha kamashma lan keditanya, teaching me
like we taught in a ברייתא. baraita. חסר שאין בו אלא מאתיים.
Chaser she'ein bo ela matayim. Let's say somebody is lacking limbs and
they only get 200 bones. רש"י Rashi does the math, if a
person is lacking sufficient number of fingers and toes, each finger is
considered and toe apparently has six bones. At least that's what רש"י
Rashi says that the גמרא Gemara is assuming. I have, I didn't
check it out on Wikipedia or anything. Anyway, so if you're missing
enough fingers and toes, you'll get down from 248, right, if you're
missing eight digits, eight times six is 48, you'll get down to
200 bones. Okay, so let's say somebody only has 200 bones. ויתר
שיש בו מאתיים ושמונים, Veyeter sheyesh bo matayim ushmonim, or somebody has
extra digits which gives them up to 280 bones. רש"י Rashi doesn't,
can't, says he can't figure out exactly how the math works on
that. Anyway, ואחד, ve'echad, 281. כולן עולין למניין קכ"ה. Kulan olin le-minyan
kuf chaf hei. This is what I mentioned before, the number 125
doesn't change. Don't, you don't adjust the number of 125 based on
the actual bones that this person has. That's a base number based
on the normal bones of a body. And not only that, if
a person has extra bones, they can count towards that number as
well, like we saw, if the digits of the hand are in
a row with, if it's in a row with the other digits
of the hand. כולן עולין, Kulan olin, so 125 is always the
number regardless of the person. זיל בתר רובא דאינשי, Zil batar ruba
de-inshi, you go by the majority of people. אמר רבי יהודה אמר
שמואל, Amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Shmuel, מעשה, ma'aseh, רבי יהודה אמר שמואל
Rabbi Yehuda amar Shmuel says a very, very famous case we're about
to read. Everybody loves quoting this because it talks about how the
rabbis actually were somewhat, sometimes did empirical studies. Let's take a look.
מעשה בתלמידיו של רבי ישמעאל, Ma'aseh betalmidav shel Rabbi Yishmael, story with
the students of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, ששלקו זונה אחת שנתחייבה שריפה
למלך, sheshalku zonah achat shenitchayva sreifah lamelech, that there was a certain
prostitute that was executed by the king, the Roman government. And presumably
they managed to acquire her body, this is how they used to
do medical studies, right, they would do grave, you know, they would,
people would, exhumed graves or were grave robbers and so on. So
they actually bought the body off of the king and then they
שלקו, shalku, which presumably means they boiled her in order to remove
the skin so that they could examine the human anatomy. So Yes,
it is pretty graphic and gruesome, but it also you know is
it it's counterweighted by the vast number of times where it seems
like their medical knowledge and scientific knowledge was by tradition and not
by empirical. But here's one story of where they actually looked at
something empirically, בדקו ומצאו בה מאתים וחמשים ושנים. badku umatzu bah matayim
vachamishim ushnayim. They found that she had 252 bones and not the
248 which we're told that people have. So אמר להם, amar lahem,
so Rabbi Ishmael says to them, שמא באשה בדקתם? shema be'isha bedaktem?
Maybe it was a woman. Well, she was a prostitute, זונה, zona,
right? But maybe, but maybe he didn't, they didn't tell him that
or maybe it was his way of telling them the fact that
it was a woman led to the difference. Why? שהוסיף לה הכתוב
שני צירים ושני דלתות. shehosif lah hakatuv shenei tzirim ushnei delatot. That
the Torah has given women, I'm going to say what it means
in the Torah, the פסוקים, psukim, but we're going to learn it
from a פסוק, pasuk, but it means God has given them basically
four extra bones, two hinges and two doors, which is presumably is
going to be understood to mean in the pelvic area, you know,
relating to, relating to the womb. But of course, I think, I
don't get it, I mean those are all the, and there's no
bone there, right? Those are all internal organs without bones. So I
don't know if that's true at all, whether women's skeleton has more
bones than a men's skeleton, but that's what the גמרא Gemara assumes
and it relates it to childbirth and what it really is doing
here, go check your orthopedist, I'm very curious. What it's doing here
is the גמרא Gemara classically when it talks about women, women's internal
organs particularly relating to childbirth, has a whole house metaphor. Okay, like
for example a משנה נדה Mishna Nidda says משלו משל חכמים באשה
החדר והעלייה, mashlu mashal chachamim be'isha hachader veha'aliya, that it's spoken like
the uterus is the inner chamber and you know it speaks about
the פרוזדור, prozdor, the outer chamber, the vestibule. It uses this whole
very house metaphor which it uses in other places for women as
well. You know, the whole word in the גמרא Gemara for a
wife is דביתהו, deveiteihu, the ביתא, beita, the house of, right? And
the גמרא Gemara consistently the word בית bayit as house, you know,
where sort of the assumption of the woman as the mainstay of
the house, the domestic, and so on. So the woman's actual body
itself is metaphorized very often, you know, with these house metaphors. These
hinges and therefore here we're talking about door hinges and doors which
presumably mean the way you know about relating to the uterus and
the opening of it for childbirth. But again there it's all flesh
as there are no bones there. Or what are we finding there
James? Did you get to anything yet? Women's skeleton number of bones?
It says it doesn't differentiate. It's 206. 206 bones? Yeah, the modern.
Infants are 270 to 300. What? Okay, some bones I guess fuse.
On the other hand, you said 200 in modern? Yeah, he says
modern anatomy says there are 206 bones in the adult skeleton. Okay,
very impressive. Art actually actually brought in the actual field facts. Variably
a variable number of sesamoid bones, small roundish bones that are embedded
in tendons or joint capsules. Ah, so that's how maybe the גמרא's
Gemara number anyway but there's no difference. Type in like just type
in Google see if there a difference men, you know, men skeletons
women see if you come up with. They generally use men as
the standard. Oh yeah, because of the fact that oh woman is
different, meaning until this was pointed out we we just would have
said 248, right? They're always using men. But now they're saying women
are consistently 252? Yeah, because when we do that מי שברך לחולים
Mi Shebeirach l'cholim always. No, that is why we say מי שברך
לחולים Mi Shebeirach l'cholim we say לכל אבריה ולכל גידיה. l'chol evareha
u'l'chol gideiha. Right when we say when we say the רמ"ח אברים
ושס"ה גידים, ramach evarim v'shasah gidim, maybe you'd say for a woman
whatever it is. That's a good question. Why don't we just switch
the number? That's a good question. Maybe getting points to the idea
that we want don't we want our standard which is okay half
the population but defined by men to sort be the the number
or maybe they're saying there is a variation in the number. Well
we're going to see in a minute there's a debate whether women
have four extra or five extra. So maybe that's why. Maybe but
I think maybe it's just because we don't want the standard you
know to be to be confused. Okay so let's take a look.
תניא Tanya we taught רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer כשם שצירים
לבית כך צירים לאשה. keshem shetzirim labayit kach tzirim la'isha. The same
way there are hinges on a house as if we missed the
metaphor there are hinges on a woman שנאמר shene'emar ותכרע ותלד vatichra
vateleid and she crouched down and she gave birth כי נהפכו עליה
ציריה ki nehepchu aleiha tzireiha because her צירים tzirim which means really
child pains pangs צירי לידה tzirei leida means pangs but here it's
being translated as hinges have turned on her which basically means the
hinges you know turned so the doors of the womb opened up.
רבי יהושע אומר Rabbi Yehoshua omer כשם שדלתות לבית keshem shedlatot labayit
the same way there are there are doors on a house כך
דלתות לאשה kach dlatot la'isha the same for a woman שנאמר shene'emar
כי לא סגר דלתי בטני ki lo sagar daltei bitni you did
not seal the doors of my womb. So there again presumably this
is relating to the doors and the hinges understanding of the Pelvis
looks different, structure's different, but they consider the pelvis one bone. So
maybe the Gemara considered it different. Pelvis were different. Yeah, it's a
common biblical myth that men have more—biblical myth? Yeah, because it says
bone between the ribs or the—Oh, because of the extra rib from
Adam. Oh, meaning that would men have a fewer bones. That's interesting.
Okay. What counts as a bone? Yeah, right. Okay, anyway, here they're
clearly understanding it relating to childbirth and relating to the womb. Okay.
רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva omer כשם שמפתח לבית keshem shemafteach labayit
ah, we have the doors and we have the hinges, but what
about the key? So the same way there's a key to a
house, כך מפתח לאשה kach mafteach leisha she's got an extra bone
that actually also is the key that somehow I don't know, maybe
that's what opens the door during childbirth, there's some bone that interacts
with the other bones and causes I'm guessing that's what he's imagining
and causes you know the the womb to open up, the doors
to open up, שנאמר shenemar what? ויפתח את רחמה vayiftach et rachmah
right? God opened up her womb because when she was she was
she was childless. So the word פתח petach ויפתח vayiftach as a
מפתח. mafteach. So the Gemara says רבי עקיבא קשיא דתלמידי דרבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Akiva kashya detalmidei deRabbi Yishmael what about the empirical evidence of
the students of Rabbi Yishmael? They only found four extra bones, not
five. So דילמא dilma איידי דזוטרא aidi d'zutra because the key is
so small, אסמוכי מטמך asmuchi mitmach because they boiled her maybe it
had dissolved, so they didn't find it. But there's a fifth bone.
אמר רב Amar Rav or some say רבא Rava and this is
which is interesting, you know, this is where like you know his
view from a פסוק pasuk is—Exactly, exactly. That's and that's the traditional
way it works. It's you know yes here it's a nice Gemara
about empirical evidence, but normally we've got our פסוקים psukim we'll interpret
the evidence accordingly, or our traditions. Anyways, אמר רב Amar Rav וכולן
אין מטמאין באהל vechulan ein metamin beohel none of these extra bones
cause טומאת אהל tumat ohel presumably whether now normally bones don't, but
presumably it means that if they add to the 125, or maybe
it means that if they have some flesh on them they're not
considered a limb by themselves. We're going to talk about these extra
bones in a moment. We are talking about these. So רש"י Rashi
says it means that if they have some flesh on them because
you need flesh to be considered a limb. Of course it's funny
because the Gemara imagined that they were completely interior, imagined that they
had flesh on them interior as well. I don't know, anyway, that
they would not cause טומאת אבר tumat eivar שנאמר זאת התורה אדם
כי ימות באהל shenemar zot hatorah adam ki yamut beohel a person
who dies in the tent. Now you might have thought that אדם
adam is being only man, but the Gemara doesn't go that far.
It says דבר השוה לכל אדם davar hashaveh lechol adam it has
to be something that is the same for all people, humans, men
and women, and therefore these that are distinctive for women don't cause
טומאה באהל. tuma beohel. But of course you would imagine that they
would still count to the 125 because if an extra finger counts
to the 125 bones, meaning as a bone not as a limb,
that these bones would as well. The only question is that if
for a woman's skeleton according to the way the Gemara imagines it,
did you need 125 or did you need 120 you know 27?
Again, it sounds like the Gemara is not moving from its number
125, which again gets to your question of why we say רמ"ח
אברים remach evarim we're still defining the number based on men. Okay.
So 125 corresponds with a positive מצוות mitzvot or something? Yeah, well
not 125, 248. We use the 248 and the 365 to be
also representing the positive and the negative מצוות. mitzvot. Yeah, so that
is like the standard number. We don't want to have two numbers
going on here. Okay. So the Gemara says like this, אמר ליה
אביי amar lei Abaye ובישה ליכא? uveisha leika? You're telling me there
are no extra bones in a man, none of these hinges? וכתיב
צירים אחזוני כצירי יולדה vachtiv tzirim achazuni ketzirei yoledah that again means
like pangs have have seized me like the like childbirth pangs. But
it's a comparison but we're reading this where ציר tzir means like
a hinge. So the Gemara says צירי בשר tzierei basar no, that's
only pure flesh that whatever that hinge means and it's not with
a bone. וכתיב אדוני במראה נהפכו צירי vachtiv adoni bemareh nehepchu tzirai
my master in a vision my again my ציר tzir my pangs,
but here we're reading like my hinges have turned. So הכא נמי
צירי בשר hacha nami tzierei basar it's only of some type of
a flesh thing, it's not with a bone. הכא נמי מסתברא hacha
nami mistabra this also makes sense, דאי לא תימא הכא de'ilam lo
teima hacha if it would not say that, מאתיים וארבעים ושמונה היכי
משכחת לה? matayan ve'arba'im ushmoneh heichi mishkachat lah? Where do we get
the number 248? לא באיש ולא באשה lo be'ish velo be'ishah not
man or woman? So it's got to be that it's metaphorically by
men, but it means it literally by women, and therefore we have
these extra things. But again quite fascinating if you bring this together
with as I said a משנה בנדה Mishnah in Niddah and other
things where a woman is a house and the interior parts of
a woman that are unique woman's anatomy are compared to the whole
sense of a house and the general larger metaphor that that speaks
towards, and here we're actually talking about the hinges and the doors.
Let's try to do a quick read of at least the next
משנה. Mishnah. יתר בידו וברגליו yeter beyado uveraglav so we're going to
start talking about the ambidextrous and all that? No, we're not up
to it yet. אמר זפתא Amar Zifta now we're talking about somebody
that has six digits on a hand and the feet. So אמר
זפתא Amar Zifta ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו ushneihem mikra echad darshu they
both interpreting one פסוק pasuk whether it is or is not a
problem. So ויהי עוד מלחמה בגת, vayehi od milchamah begat, there was
another war in Gat that says at the end of David's career,
this is not at the beginning with גלית. Golyas. ויהי איש מדון,
vayehi ish madon, there was a person of great stature, אצבע אצבעות
ידיו ואצבעות רגליו שש שש, etzba etzbaot yadav ve'etzbaot raglav sheish sheish,
he had six fingers on each hand and six toes on each
foot, ועשרים וארבע, ve'esrim ve'arba, 24 digits, so that's the whole פסוק.
pasuk. So there you got a person that's this משנה. mishnah. מר
סבר לגנותי משתעי, mar savar lagnusei mishtayei, one assumes that the verse
is sort of saying it, you know, as an insult, denigrating him,
look at this freak of nature, ומר סבר לשבחי משתעי, umar savar
leshvachei mishtayei, it's praising him like, wow, look at this, he's not
only tall, he has extra digits also like what a, you know,
what a powerful foe. So אמר רבא מאי דכתיב שש שש עשרים
וארבע, amar Rava mai de'kesiv sheish sheish esrim ve'arba, so that's how
one opinion says that if you have if it's parallel symmetrical then
it's actually not a problem. That'll be רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That's
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Right, and it's also the same רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that didn't have a problem with the hunchback. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has a small, you know, maybe has a consistent
approach here to not not make as many things מום. mum. And
let's just get to the משנה. mishnah. אמר רבא מאי דכתיב שש
שש עשרים וארבע, amar Rava mai de'kesiv sheish sheish esrim ve'arba, why
does it say 6, 6, 24? What, I can't do math? מספר
צריכי? mispar tzrichi? Do you have to tell me how to count?
So no. דאי כתב רחמנא שש ושש, de'ee kesav rachmana sheish ve'sheish,
if it just said 6, 6, הוה אמינא שש דידי ושש דכרעי,
hava amina sheish de'yadei ve'sheish de'karei, it would I would have said
there be a six, an extra six on one hand, an extra
six on a foot, but I wouldn't have assumed it meant both
hands and both feet. כתיב עשרים וארבע, kesiv esrim ve'arba, so it
says 24 to tell me it means six on every single on
each, both hands and on both feet. ואי כתיב עשרים וארבע, ve'ee
kesiv esrim ve'arba, if it just said 24, הוה אמינא הא חמישה
מהאי גיסא ושבעה מהאי גיסא, hava amina ha chamisha me'hai gisa ve'shiva
me'hai gisa, maybe it would have been five on one hand and
seven on the other, I wouldn't have assumed it meant six on
each. I think there was a baby born that had six... really?
Today. כתיב שש שש. kesiv sheish sheish. Okay, so it just says
6, 6 and 24 to tell me exactly how they were distributed.
Then why does it say מספר, mispar, in number? So it says
בנספרת benisperet to tell me the thing we said before that when
it might be considered less of a problem or when it's considered
more of a digit, more of an organ, it's when more of
a limb, it's when it is in line with the other finger.
So that was the word מספר mispar means it's counted with the
other fingers, it's in line with the other fingers. Okay. בנספרת על
גבי היד תנא. benisperet al gabei ha'yad tanna. ואמר רבי יהודה מעשה
באדם אחד שבא לפני רבי טרפון. ve'amar Rabbi Yehuda ma'aseh be'adam echad
she'ba lifnei Rabbi Tarfon. There was a person that came in front
of רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. ויש בידו וברגליו שש שש עשרים וארבע,
ve'yeish beyado uveraglav sheish sheish esrim ve'arba, just a case like in
our משנה, mishnah, like he had extra digits, 24. אמר לו amar
lo he said to him, כמוך ירבו בישראל, kamoch yarbu be'Yisrael, like
you should be many in, you know, in Israel. So that was
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda proof, ah, this is better! You have extra
limbs and as long as it's all symmetrical it's not a מום.
mum. אמר לו רבי יוסי, amar lo Rabbi Yosei, so רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei retorted back, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei presumably being the תנא
קמא tanna kamma who assumes that this is a מום. mum. So
he says משם ראיה, misham re'ayah, there you want to bring a
proof? כך אמר לו, kach amar lo, he didn't just say, oh,
you know, there should be many like you. You missed the whole
story, here's what he said: כמוך ימעטו ממזרים ונתינים בישראל. kamoch yim'atu
mamzerim ve'nesinim be'Yisrael. If people, if there are more like you, then
there will be fewer ממזרים mamzerim in Israel, why? Because there is
a belief that people these deformities sometimes would come as a result
of sins, sexual sins, or some another גמרא Gemara thinks it has
to do with actually improper thoughts during sex, but sexual sin. So
he assumed that he was a result of an adulterous relationship and
that's why he had this, you know, this deformity. So he said
if more of this would happen people would see the results of
adulterous relationships it would be less adultery, less ממזרים. mamzerim. So that
was the story and not that he thought it was a good
thing. Right, exactly. Was it a compliment or an insult? Exactly. I
guess if they were a lot of ממזרים mamzerim then well... why
not? Well because he's like saying הלוואי halevai there were more like
you so הלוואי halevai that all of the all of the ממזרים
mamzerim would look like you... right... right, but I don't know if
it means הלוואי הלוואי halevai halevai all the ממזרים mamzerim would look
like you so that in any case there were ממזרים. mamzerim. Yeah
well... definitely. Definitely. Okay so just to finish to the משנה mishnah
this is very relevant to me. I will tell you I am
now פסול pasul to serve in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash already
for one reason other than not being a כהן, Kohen, which is
that I have, anybody can guess which מום mum so far? I
have an outie. Okay, that's a מום mum so far... exactly... and
now we're going to get to the other reason I'm פסול pasul
cause I'm a lefty. Okay so השולט בשתי ידיו, hasholet bishtei yadav,
if you're ambidextrous. תנו רבנן איטר, Tanu Rabbanan iter, if somebody's a
left handed, בין ביד בין ברגל, bein beyad bein beragel, even a
left footed. Now how do you determine that? So רש"י Rashi says
and this actually is interesting, you can try this. Have somebody stand
straight and say walk to me and see which foot they put
out first... left foot, the left... so most often it's the same
as the handedness. Okay, so השולט... איטר בין ביד בין ברגל iter
bein beyad bein beragel whether the hand or in the foot פסול
pasul is invalid if you're left handed. I'll talk about why in
a minute, let's just finish the גמרא. Gemara. השולט בשתי ידיו. hasholet
bishtei yadav. If you're ambidextrous, רבי פסול וחכמים מכשירים. Rebbi posul veChachamim
machshirin. רבי Rebbi says no good, חכמים Chachamim say it's good. מר
סבר תכישותא אתחלה בימין, Mar savar tachishusha atchila beyamin, it's a weakness
of the right hand. ומר סבר בריותא אתחלה בשמאל, U-mar savar briyusa
atchila bismol, it's a strength of the left hand. Now which one
makes it, which one is good, which one is not good? So
you would think that it means, presumably what it means is that
if it's just a stronger left hand, so it's not that there's
a problem with your right, you just have a strength in your
left. That's not a פסול. pasul. If it's a weakness of your
right, so then that is a פסול. pasul. But I wonder if
you could say the opposite. If you say it's just a weakness
of the right, then we're saying you're basically right-handed but your right
is a little weak. But if you're emphasizing the strength of the
left, that's maybe somewhat designating you as left-handed and maybe that's more
of a problem. But the assumption is the opposite, that if it's
just a strength of the left, it's not a פסול, pasul, if
it's a weakness of the right, so then that is a פסול.
pasul. Now why is left-handedness a problem? So you could have said
it's like the, I don't know, like again, the outy belly button,
which is just that it's not within some normal range and the
standard, I mean there's a normal range, right, exactly. So but again,
that's why the belly button is an interesting example because it's very
normal, it's just not the majority of the population but certainly very
normal. So you could have said that. But רש"י Rashi says something
different. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, very important רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi says, איטר, iter, so in the middle of רש"י, Rashi, איטר
ברגל, iter baregel, he says, כך איטר ביד פסול דכתיב וטבל אצבעו
כל מקום שנאמר אצבע בכהן אינו אלא ימין. kach iter beyad pasul
dechtiv utaval etzba'o kol makom shene'emar etzba bakohen eino ela yamin. Okay,
that when you have to dip your right hand and therefore the
תורה Torah emphasis, emphasizes your right hand. So you have to dip
when you use, the תורה Torah speaks about the way a כהן
kohen does things with his hand, it has to be right hand.
Now presumably there's an assumption that that also has to be your
dominant hand. If you're a lefty, you can't use your right hand.
It has to both be right and dominant and therefore it's a
problem of doing the עבודה. avodah. That's the way רש"י Rashi reads
it, but if that's true, one minute, then the, then the left-footedness
is not so clear. So רש"י Rashi goes on to say, ואיטר
דרגלו נמי לעמוד ולשרת כתיב כדרך שאר עמידה דקירוב בימין, ve'iter dereglen
nami la'amod uleshares ketiv kederach shaar amida dikarov beyamin, that you have
to sort of stand and not only stand but maybe move. So
your movement has to be like most כהנים kohanim which is your
right foot first. So somehow it is less of a problem that
you are a מום mum or not שוה בזרעו של אהרן shaveh
bezaro shel Aharon and more of a problem that in the act
of עבודה avodah you have to do it with your right being
dominant. So it's very interesting conceptually new category, right, which is funny
because that's not the sense that you get here, but רש"י Rashi
somehow did not want to perhaps say that whatever the percentage of
the population it is, twenty-five percent or whatever the percentage is, my
entire family, me, my wife, my two kids, we're all left-handed. Anyway,
so anyway, perhaps רש"י Rashi felt that this was too big of
a slice of the population to even say it's not זרעו של
אהרן. zaro shel Aharon. So רש"י Rashi emphasizes that the problem here
is that the act of the עבודה avodah requires the right and
the right being dominant. It's an interesting way of framing it and
it takes two right hand and right foot together, not, you can't
be like, if you're left foot, no, no, either one, no they
assume it could be different and that's why they say if you're,
if you're not, if you're left footed and not, or even if
you're even only left footed or only left handed, that is enough
to invalidate. But again, it's interesting that he makes it not a
פסול pasul problem and not even a זרעו של אהרן zaro shel
Aharon but an act of an עבודה avodah problem and then the
question remains with practical, a very practical. But then the question really
remains then why should ambidextrous be an issue? Because since by ambidextrous
you still have, it's, but maybe again, maybe it has to really
be dominant, not just have be equal strength. But that is at
least the way רש"י Rashi reads and we will continue with this.
The incidences of left-handedness and outy belly buttons.